William Edward Dodd Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
William Edward Dodd Papers 1895-1955 (bulk 1900-1940)
MSS18697
Dodd, William Edward, 1869-1940
22,000 items
64 containers plus 1 oversize
25.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Historian and diplomat. Correspondence, diaries, speeches, writings, autobiographical notes, printed matter, photographs, and other papers relating to Dodd's work as an author, professor of history at the University of Chicago, and ambassador to Germany.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Baker, Newton Diehl, 1871-1937--Correspondence.; Becker, Carl L. (Carl Lotus), 1873-1945--Correspondence.; Beveridge, Albert Jeremiah, 1862-1927--Correspondence.; Bowers, Claude Gernade, 1879-1958--Correspondence.; Brett, George P. (George Platt), 1858-1936--Correspondence.; Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1862-1947--Correspondence.; Daniels, Josephus, 1862-1948--Correspondence.; Dodd family--Correspondence.; Dodd, Martha Johns, -1938--Correspondence.; Dodd, Martha, 1908-1990--Correspondence.; Dodd, William E. (William Edward), 1869-1940.; House, Edward Mandell, 1858-1938--Correspondence.; Hull, Cordell, 1871-1955--Correspondence.; Moore, R. Walton (Robert Walton), 1859-1941--Correspondence.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945--Correspondence.; Roper, Daniel C. (Daniel Calhoun), 1867-1943--Correspondence.; Sandburg, Carl, 1878-1967. Carl Sandburg poetry drafts.; Schacht, Hjalmar Horace Greeley, 1877-1970--Correspondence.; Turner, Frederick Jackson, 1861-1932--Correspondence.
Organizations
University of Chicago.
Subjects
Diplomatic and consular service, American--Germany.; World politics--20th century.
Places
Chicago (Ill.)--Politics and government.; Europe--Description and travel.; Germany--Foreign relations--United States.; Illinois--Politics and government.; United States--Foreign relations--Germany.; United States--History.; United States--Politics and government--20th century.
Occupations
Diplomats.; Historians.
Provenance
The papers of William Edward Dodd, historian and diplomat, were received by the Library as a deposit in 1945 and 1953 from Dodd's son, William E. Dodd, Jr., and daughter, Martha Dodd Stern. Stern added further papers as gifts in 1964, 1969, and 1972, and as a deposit in 1981. In 1965 the 1945 deposit was converted to a gift. Additional material came through gift and purchase, 1952-1979. In 1989, the remainder of the collection was converted to a gift.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of William Edward Dodd are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1869, Oct. 21 Born, Clayton, N.C.
1897 B.S. and M.S., Virginia Polytechnic Institute, Blacksburg, Va.
1899 Ph.D., University of Leipzig, Leipzig, Germany
1901 Married Martha Johns
1900 1908 Professor of history, Randolph-Macon College, Ashland, Va.
1908 1933 Professor of history, University of Chicago, Chicago, Ill.
1933 1937 Ambassador to Germany
1934 President, American Historical Association
1938 1940 Returned and resided in the United States
1940, Feb. 9 Died, Round Hill, Va.
1941 Publication of Ambassador Dodd's Diary, 1933-1937. New York: Harcourt, Brace and Co.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of William Edward Dodd (1869-1940) span the years 1895 to 1955, with the bulk of the material dating from 1900 to 1940. The papers are in English and German with French and are organized in six series: General Correspondence, Speeches and Writings, Miscellany, Family Correspondence, Addition, and Oversize. Included are two pocket diaries from 1928 and 1931, articles, speeches, book material, autobiographical notes relating to Dodd's life before 1930, a correspondence file, much of it within the family, from 1895 until 1953 long after his death, and letters written by Dodd during a trip to Europe, 1928-1929. The earlier papers relate to Dodd's work as an historian, author, and citizen-scholar interested in local, state, national, and international politics. The greater part of the papers concern Dodd's career as professor of history at the University of Chicago and as ambassador to Germany.
Prominent correspondents include Newton Diehl Baker, Carl L. Becker, Albert Jeremiah Beveridge, Claude Gernade Bowers, George P. Brett, Nicholas Murray Butler, Josephus Daniels, Edward Mandell House, Cordell Hull, R. Walton Moore, Franklin D. Roosevelt, Daniel C. Roper, Hjalmar Horace Greeley Schacht, and Frederick Jackson Turner, as well as many other scholars and diplomatic colleagues. Family correspondents include Dodd's wife, Martha Johns Dodd, and their daughter, Martha Dodd (Stern).
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in six series:
General Correspondence, 1900-1953
Speeches and Writings, 1911-1938
Miscellany, 1928-1941
Family Correspondence, 1895-1953
Addition, 1929-1955
Oversize, 1935
Container List
- General Correspondence, 1900-1953 (Box 1-57)
  Correspondence.
  Arranged chronologically by year and alphabetically therein.
  - 1900-1903 (Box 1)
  - 1902-1904 (Box 2)
  - 1904-1905 (Box 3)
  - 1905-1907 (Box 4)
  - 1907 (Box 5)
  - 1907-1908 (Box 6)
  - 1909-1910 (Box 7)
  - 1910-1912 (Box 8)
  - 1912-1913 (Box 9)
  - 1913-1914 (Box 10)
  - 1914-1915 (Box 11)
  - 1916-1917 (Box 12)
  - 1918-1919 (Box 13)
  - 1919 (Box 14)
    - A-S (Box 14)
    - T-Z (Box 15)
  - 1920 (Box 15)
    - A-Z (Box 15)
    - N-Z (Box 16)
  - 1921 (Box 16)
  - 1921, Sept.-1922, Apr. (Box 17)
  - 1922 (Box 17)
    - A-G (Box 17)
    - H-Z (Box 18)
  - 1923 (Box 18)
  - 1923, Oct.-1925, Mar. (Box 19)
  - 1924 (Box 19)
    - A-Q (Box 19)
    - R-Z (Box 20)
  - 1924, Oct.-1925, Mar. (Box 20)
  - 1925 (Box 20)
    - May-July (Box 20)
      - A-H (Box 20)
      - K-Z (Box 21)
    - Aug.-Sept. (Box 21)
    - Oct.-Dec. (Box 21)
      - A-L (Box 21)
      - M-Z (Box 22)
    - A-Z (Box 22)
  - 1925, American Historical Association program (Box 22)
  - 1925 (Box 22)
  - 1926 (Box 23)
  - 1926 (Box 24)
  - 1927 (Box 25)
    - Jan.-Apr. (Box 25)
      - A-H (Box 25)
      - K-Z (Box 26)
    - Apr.-July (Box 26)
    - July-Oct. (Box 27)
    - Oct.-Dec. (Box 27)
      - A-G (Box 27)
      - S-Z (Box 28)
  - 1928, Jan.-May (Box 28)
  - 1928 (Box 29)
    - Jan.-Apr. (Box 29)
    - May-July (Box 29)
      - A-F (Box 29)
      - C-Z (Box 30)
    - July-Aug. (Box 30)
      - A-L (Box 30)
      - M-Z (Box 31)
  - 1928-1929 (Box 31)
  - Late 1928-early 1929, trip to Europe (Box 31)
    - A-M (Box 31)
    - N-Z (Box 32)
  - 1929-1930 (Box 32)
  - 1929-1930 (Box 33)
  - 1929-1930 (Box 34)
  - 1930 (Box 35)
  - 1930 (Box 36)
  - 1931 (Box 36)
    - Mar. 16-May 1 (Box 36)
      - A-O (Box 36)
      - A-C (Box 37)
      - D-Z (Box 38)
  - 1931, Dec.-1932, May (Box 38)
    - A-O (Box 38)
    - P-Z (Box 39)
  - 1932 (Box 39)
  - 1933 (Box 40)
    - A-F (Box 40)
    - G-L (Box 41)
    - M-R (Box 42)
    - S-Z (Box 43)
  - 1934 (Box 43)
    - A-C (Box 43)
    - E-M (Box 44)
    - M-Z (Box 45)
  - 1935 (Box 46)
    - A-K (Box 46)
    - L-S (Box 47)
    - T-Z (Box 48)
  - 1936 (Box 48)
    - A-G (Box 48)
    - H-R (Box 49)
    - S-Z (Box 50)
  - 1937 (Box 50)
    - A-C (Box 50)
    - D-G (Box 51)
    - H-Z (Box 52)
  - 1938 (Box 53)
    - Jan.-Feb. (Box 53)
    - Jan.-Apr. (Box 54)
    - Mar.-July (Box 55)
    - July-Oct. (Box 56)
    - Sept.-Dec. (Box 57)
  - 1939 (Box 57)
    - Jan.-Apr. (Box 57)
      - A-D (Box 57)
      - E-Z (Box 58)
    - May-Nov. (Box 58)
  - 1939-1953, undated (Box 58)
- Speeches and Writings, 1911-1938 (Box 59-60)
  Writings by Dodd, including autobiographical notes, academic articles and reviews, speeches, editorials, and book material.
  Arranged chronologically by year and alphabetically by title therein, with untitled items at the end.
  - Undated, autobiographical notes (Box 59)
  - 1911, "The Fight for the Northwest, 1860," papers read before the American Historical Association, Dec. 30, 1910: American Historical Review, XVI, no. 4, July 1911 (Box 59)
  - 1925 (Box 59)
    - "Little Men of Great Influence: Lecture III, Robert Walker; Lecture IV, Theodore Roosevelt" (Box 59)
    - "When Washington Tried Isolation," Arts and Sciences (Box 59)
  - 1928, "Cross Currents in American Politics," outline of Cincinnati, Ohio, speech, Jan. 27 (Box 59)
  - 1929, book review of The Tragic Era, by Claude Bowers (Box 59)
  - 1932, "George Washington," Study for Vanderbilt Lectures, Vanderbilt University, Nashville, Tenn., Feb. 22-23 (Box 59)
  - 1933 (Box 59)
    - "Back to the Land?" editorial (Box 59)
    - "The Federal Constitution and Its Application, 1789 to 1933" (Box 59)
    - "The Federal Constitution and the Economic Effects of Its Administration" (Box 59)
    - "The First Stratified Society in the United States," Munich, Germany, Dec. 5 (Box 59)
    - "Frank Stringfellow," sketch (Box 59)
    - "German Contribution to American Life," radio address, Oct. 6 (Box 59)
    - "Greatest Blunder in Modern History" (Box 59)
    - "Martin Luther," Berlin, Germany, Nov.19 (Box 59)
    - "What Is the Matter with the Country?" (Box 59)
    - "The Worse Economic Dilemma of Modern History," editorial (Box 59)
    - "Preface" to book by Helmut Magers, Oct. (Box 59)
    - Untitled dinner address, June 23 (Box 59)
  - 1934 (Box 59)
    - "A Troubled World," Bremen, Germany, Sept. 9 (Box 59)
    - "Subjects of Study," Berlin, Germany, June 26 (Box 59)
    - "Woodrow Wilson," Encyclopaedia of the Social Sciences (Box 59)
    - Book review of Woodrow Wilson, by Edith Gittings (Box 59)
    - Untitled article for Griffin of the Chicago Tribune, May 16 (Box 59)
  - 1935 (Box 59)
    - "Abraham Lincoln and His Problem, 1861," Berlin, Germany, June 14 (Box 59)
    - "The International Dilemma" (Box 59)
    - "The Problem of Recovery" (Box 59)
    - "The Urgent Problems," Berlin, Germany, Nov. 28 (Box 59)
    - Untitled speeches, June 4 and July 24 (Box 59)
  - 1936 (Box 59)
    - "The Problem of Modern Civilization" (Box 59)
    - "On Wilson's 80th Birthday," New York Times, Dec. 27 (Box 59)
    - "The Struggle for Democracy," Chicago, Ill., July 7 (Box 59)
    - "Thomas Jefferson," Berlin, Germany, Apr. 16 (Box 59)
    - Statements to radio and press (Box 59)
      - Aug. 16, re: Olympic Games (Box 59)
      - Nov. 4, re-election of Franklin D. Roosevelt (Box 59)
    - Untitled radio speech, Berlin, Germany, Oct. 6 (Box 59)
    - Untitled speech brief, Cleveland, Ohio, July 22 (Box 59)
  - 1937 (Box 59)
    - "Can Democracy Be Preserved?" Williamstown, Mass., Sept. 3 (Box 59)
    - "The Dangerous Drift of To-day," Washington & Lee University, Lexington, Va., Sept. 17 (Box 59)
    - "Do unto Others as You Would Have Others Do unto You," Berlin, Germany, May 30 (Box 59)
    - "George Washington and the American Union," Leipzig, Germany, Dec. 16 (Box 59)
    - "The Unique Function of Education in American Democracy" (Box 59)
    - "Von Steuben," Magdeburg, Germany, May 21 (Box 59)
    - Untitled radio speech, Williamstown, Mass., Sept. 3 (Box 59)
  - 1938 (Box 60)
    - "Arrival Message," New York, Jan. 8 (Box 60)
    - "The New German Education" (Box 60)
    - "Racial-Religious Reforms in Germany" (Box 60)
    - "The Threatening German Dictatorship" (Box 60)
  - Undated (Box 60)
    - "Better Government," editorial (Box 60)
    - "The Curious German State" (Box 60)
    - "The Emergence of the First Social Order in the United States" (Box 60)
    - "Henry White Davis, Embittered Statesman" (Box 60)
    - "Karl Lamprecht and Kulturgeschichte" (Box 60)
    - "Lessons of the Great War" (Box 60)
    - "The Place of Nathaniel Macon in Southern History" (Box 60)
    - "Should Not the Majority Govern?" (Box 60)
    - "The Status of Higher Education in Virginia" (Box 60)
    - "The University and the Public" (Box 60)
    - "Introduction" to William T. Hutchinson's book (Box 60)
    - Untitled and miscellaneous manuscripts (Box 60)
- Miscellany, 1928-1941 (Box 60-61)
  Diaries, photographs, printed matter, and other material.
  Arranged by type of material.
  - Reception and dinner lists, 1934-1937, (2 folders) (Box 60)
  - Listing of doctors of philosophy (Box 60)
  - Printed matter, 1935-1938 (Box 60)
  - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings, 1928-1941 (Box 61)
  - Photographs, 1936, undated (Box 61)
  - Diaries, 1928, 1931 (Box 61)
- Family Correspondence, 1895-1953 (Box 62-63)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - Dodd, David (brother), 1935-1937, undated (Box 62)
  - Dodd, David, Jr. (nephew), 1937 (Box 62)
  - Dodd, Jay Hubbard (daughter-in-law), 1952 (Box 62)
  - Dodd, Martha (daughter) 1926-1937 See Container 63, Stern, Martha Dodd (Box 62)
  - Dodd, Martha Johns (wife), 1896-1938, (9 folders) (Box 62)
  - Dodd, Roscoe S. (cousin), 1937, Feb. 8-Aug. 10 (Box 63)
  - Dodd, Walter H., Dec. 5, 1933-Oct. 4, 1937 (Box 63)
  - Dodd, William Edward, Jr. (son), 1932, Dec. 13-1952, Oct. 30, undated, (6 folders) (Box 63)
  - Griffin, Annie Dodd (sister), 1933-1937 (Box 63)
  - Haynes, Margaret Dodd (niece), 1934, Oct. 28 (Box 63)
  - Horne, Herman H. (cousin), 1934, Apr.-1936, Dec. (Box 63)
  - Horne, Ida B. (cousin), 1934, Aug. 9-1936, Mar. 18 (Box 63)
  - Johns, Clarence D. (brother-in-law), 1936, Feb. 24-1937, May 15 (Box 63)
  - Johns, Eva (sister-in-law), 1895-1900 (Box 63)
  - Stern, Alfred K. (son-in-law), 1952, July 31- Nov. 20 (Box 63)
  - Stern, Martha Dodd (daughter), 1926, Sept. 29-1937, July 25, (3 folders) (Box 63)
  - Sturdivant, Evangeline J. (niece), 1934-1935 (Box 63)
- Addition, 1901-1955 (Box 64)
  Correspondence, photographs, news clippings, and miscellany.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material with miscellany at the end.
  - General correspondence, 1901-1955, (13 folders) (Box 64)
  - Writings file, poetry by Carl Sandburg (Box 64)
  - Miscellany (Box 64)
    - Photographs, (2 folders) (Box 64)
    - Sketches (Box 64)
    - Clippings (Box 64)
    - Lock of hair (Carl Sandburg) (Box 64)
    - Diploma of William E. Dodd, Jr., 1935 See Oversize (Box 64)
- Oversize, 1935 (Box OV 1)
  Diploma.
  Described according to the series, container, and folder from which the item was removed.
  - Addition (Box OV 1)
    - Miscellany (Box OV 1)
      - Diploma of William E. Dodd, Jr., 1935 (Container 64) (Box OV 1)